Guide to the Helena Woman's Club Records 1896-1995
Montana Historical Society Archives
Helena Woman's Club Records
1896-1995
Montana Historical Society, Research Center Archives 225 N. Roberts PO Box 201201 Helena MT 59620-1201 (406) 444-4774 mhslibrary@mt.gov
MC 303
Helena Woman's Club (Helena, Mont.)
3.2 linear feet of shelf space
Records of the Helena Woman's Club include treasurer's books (1969-1995); articles of incorporation (1896); minutes of the general and Executive Board meetings (1901-1908, 1921-1940, 1947-1956, 1959-1993), of the Arts and Crafts Dept. (1915-1937,1955-1988), of the Liberal Arts Dept. (1967-1975), of the Literary Dept. (1940-1956), of the Music Dept. (1925-1946), and of the Social and Political Science Dept. (1920-1929); and yearbooks (1900-1995).
The Helena Woman's Club was formed in 1896 with the purpose of providing its members "intellectual advancement and mutual improvement". Club sponsored programs focused on art, literature, music, biographies, and history. Speakers for these programs included community leaders and club members. The first officers elected were Mrs. E. Sharpe, president; Mrs. W.R. Sanders, vice president; and Mrs. E. F. Wilson, secretary/treasurer. Membership was limited to twenty ladies. New members were elected by the full membership whenever a vacancy occured. A small number of honorary members were also allowed who could participate in meetings but not vote on officers or membership. The Helena Woman's Club became a member of the General Federation of Women's Clubs in 1901, and a member of the Montana Federation of Women's Club in 1904. The club worked on various civic enrichment projects over the years including offering scholarships to young musicians from the local schools, and serving on the board of the Restoration Committee for the Original Governor's Mansion. The Woman's Club conducted fundraisers to purchase the blue silk damask curtains for the master bedroom in the Governor's Mansion. The club currently meets once a month.
Content Description:
The records of the Helena Woman's Club include financial records (1969-1995) consisting of treasurer's books (1969-1995); minutes (1901-1993) of the general and executive board meetings (1901-1908, 1921-1940, 1947-1956, 1959-1993), of the Arts and Crafts Department (1915-1937,1955-1988), of the Liberal Arts Department (1967-1975), of the Literary Department (1940-1956), of the Music Department (1925-1946), and of the Social and Political Science Department (1920-1929); organizational records (1896, n.d.) including constitution and bylaws; and year books (1900-1995).
Arrangement:
by series
Acquisition Information:
available upon request
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Women--Societies and clubs; Helena (Mont.)--Buildings, structures, etc.; Helena (Mont.)--Social life and customs; Montana
Detailed Description of the Collection
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection
- Financial Records
  - Treasurer's book (listing receipts and expenditures including dues payments), 1969-1990 (Box-folder 1 / 1)
  - Treasurer's book (listing receipts and expenditures including dues payments), 1990-1995 (Box-folder 1 / 2)
  - Materials removed from Treasure's book, 1992 (Box-folder 1 / 3)
- Minutes
  - Minutes of regular meetings (includes constitution), 1901-1908 (Box-folder 1 / 4)
  - Minutes of regular meetings and board meetings, 1921-1922 (Box-folder 1 / 5)
  - Minutes of regular meetings and board meetings, 1923-1924 (Box-folder 1 / 6)
  - Minutes of regular meetings and board meetings, 1925 (Box-folder 1 / 7)
  - Minutes of regular meetings and board meetings, 1926-1927 (Box-folder 1 / 8)
  - Minutes of regular meetings and board meetings, 1928-1929 (Box-folder 1 / 9)
  - Minutes of regular meetings and board meetings, 1930-1931 (Box-folder 1 / 10)
  - Minutes of regular meetings and board meetings, 1932 (Box-folder 2 / 1)
  - Minutes of regular meetings and board meetings, 1933 (Box-folder 2 / 2)
  - Minutes of regular meetings and board meetings, 1934 (Box-folder 2 / 3)
  - Minutes of regular meetings and board meetings, 1935 (Box-folder 2 / 4)
  - Minutes of regular meetings and board meetings, 1936-1937 (Box-folder 2 / 5)
  - Minutes of regular meetings and board meetings, 1938 (Box-folder 2 / 6)
  - Minutes of regular meetings and board meetings, 1939-1940 (Box-folder 2 / 7)
  - Minutes of regular meetings and board meetings, 1947-1950 (Box-folder 2 / 8)
  - Minutes of regular meetings and board meetings, 1950-1952 (Box-folder 2 / 9)
  - Minutes of regular meetings and board meetings, 1953-1955 (Box-folder 2 / 10)
  - Minutes of regular meetings and board meetings, 1955-1956 (Box-folder 2 / 11)
  - Minutes of regular meetings and board meetings, 1957-1958 (Box-folder 2 / 12)
  - Minutes of regular meetings and board meetings, 1959 (Box-folder 3 / 1)
  - Minutes of regular meetings and board meetings, 1960-1961 (Box-folder 3 / 2)
  - Minutes of regular meetings and board meetings, 1963-1965 (Box-folder 3 / 3)
  - Minutes of regular meetings and board meetings, 1966-1968 (Box-folder 3 / 4)
  - Minutes of regular meetings and board meetings, 1969-1970 (Box-folder 3 / 5)
  - Minutes of regular meetings and board meetings, 1971-1973 (Box-folder 3 / 6)
  - Minutes of regular meetings and board meetings, 1973-1974 (Box-folder 3 / 7)
  - Minutes of regular meetings and board meetings, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 3 / 8)
  - Minutes of regular meetings and board meetings, 1977-1979 (Box-folder 3 / 9)
  - Minutes of regular meetings and board meetings, 1980-1982 (Box-folder 3 / 10)
  - Minutes of regular meetings and board meetings, 1983-1984 (Box-folder 3 / 11)
  - Minutes of regular meetings and board meetings, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 3 / 12)
  - Minutes of regular meetings and board meetings, 1988-1993 (Box-folder 3 / 13)
  - Minutes of Arts and Crafts Department, 1915-1926 (Box-folder 3 / 14)
  - Minutes of Arts and Crafts Department, 1926-1930 (Box-folder 4 / 1)
  - Minutes of Arts and Crafts Department, 1931-1937 (Box-folder 4 / 2)
  - Minutes of Arts and Crafts Department, 1955-1964 (Box-folder 4 / 3)
  - Minutes of Arts and Crafts Department, 1965-1972 (Box-folder 4 / 4)
  - Minutes of Arts and Crafts Department, 1973-1980 (Box-folder 4 / 5)
  - Minutes of Arts and Crafts Department, 1981-1988 (Box-folder 4 / 6)
  - Minutes of Liberal Arts Department, 1967-1975 (Box-folder 4 / 7)
  - Minutes of Literary Department, 1940-1952 (Box-folder 4 / 8)
  - Minutes of Literary Department, 1952-1956 (Box-folder 4 / 9)
  - Minutes of Music Department, 1925-1935 (Box-folder 4 / 10)
  - Minutes of Music Department, 1935-1946 (Box-folder 5 / 1)
  - Minutes of Social and Political Science Department, 1920-1929 (Box-folder 5 / 2)
- Organizational records
  - Constitution and bylaws (including revisions) [OVERSIZE MATERIAL: See map case] (Box-folder 5 / 3)
- Miscellany
  - Convention programs from the Montana Federatio of Women's Club 4th District annual meetings, 1975-1979 (Box-folder 5 / 4)
  - Cookbook titled "Looks What's Cooking" (compiled by Helena Woman's Club members), 1987 (Box-folder 5 / 5)
  - Scrapbook on the Restoration Project for the Original Governor's Mansion in Helena, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 5 / 6)
  - What Makes You Think So? (book donated to the club with inscription), 1938 (Box-folder 5 / 7)
  - Yearbooks, 1897-1916 (Box-folder 5 / 8-10)
  - Yearbooks, 1916-1979 (Box-folder 6 / 1-10)
  - Yearbooks, 1983-1996 (Box-folder 7 / 1-2)